China is one of the world's most fascinating and complicated countries,
and its cities seem to get bigger every year.
Considered a rural society just a few decades ago,
China today is home to the world's largest urban population.
I traveled to China independently for more than a decade,
on several occasions.
And in this video I will show you some of the most striking
and interesting cities I came across.
From the ancient centers of Beijing and Xian,
to the modern megacities of Shenzhen and Guangzhou.
We visit the freezing Winter festivals of Harbin
and the popular Summer holiday beaches of coastal Qingdao.
From the streets of fusion cities like Hong Kong and Macau,
we travel to Tibetan Lhasa,
located on the 'Rooftop of the World'.
We also take a look at the now historic alleys of Kashgar,
in the controversial Xinjiang province,
and the empty streets of Ordos, China's best known 'ghost town'.
And we explore the expanding urban centers along the Yangtze river,
all the way to the fast paced metropolis of Shanghai.
So join me on this journey through urban China.
We begin our travels in Shanghai, one of China's most
unique and dynamic cities.
Its iconic skyline has become a symbol of the country's
explosive economic growth of the past decades,
and provides a glimpse into the many changes China has undergone.
While it's a lot of glitz, glamour, and commerce here,
Shanghai also has some beautiful historic architecture,
peaceful parks and laidback neighborhoods.
Most travelers start their trip to Shanghai on the Bund,
a waterfront promenade lined with former Western
consulates and financial institutions.
Many of these buildings are now used as restaurants,
bars and fashion stores,
and are a stunning contrast with the modern skyline of Pudong,
Shanghai's business district.
Most farmland only 3 decades ago, this spectacle of skyscrapers
has become a major financial hub.
Some of the buildings have observation decks,
from where you can get amazing views over the city.
For those interested in China's economic story,
it may be worthwhile to hire a taxi
to the city's water port, the largest container terminal in the world.
Shanghai is a city of commerce, which is best seen
by walking Nanjing Lu,
a pedestrian only shopping street in the heart of the city.
If the crowds become overwhelming, the nearby Jing'An temple
might bring some relief,
where you can join a Buddhist ceremony, or simply escape
the hustle and bustle from the streets.
More traditional neighborhoods still exist, but you
have to look closely these days to find them.
Walking some of the narrow alleyways of this old Shanghai
is an adventure on its own,
and it's easy to get lost both in time and place.
This authentic Shanghai, however, is disappearing fast,
as many buildings are taken down,
and replaced by apartment towers and shopping malls.
Whatever you think of it, this is the story of Shanghai,
a city in constant flux, changing all the time.
And who dares to guess what it will look like in a few decades?
After Shanghai, we travel all the way North of China,
to visit Harbin,
a city of over 5 million people, with a strong historic Russian influence.
While it's a good place to visit all year, things really get busy in Winter,
when millions of people come to see the famous
Ice and Snow festival.
Thousands of workers prepare for many weeks in
bitterly cold conditions,
building temples, sculptures and palaces, all made from ice and snow.
Watching them at work may be as impressive as the festival itself.
Other than admiring the craftsmanship and artwork,
visitors can also take part in many Winter activities.
And as you walk around the festival grounds, you will see people
sledding, skating, and using ice bicycles.
While spectacular during the day, my favorite time to visit
the festival was around sunset.
At twilight, the ice sculptures are lit up with beautiful neon lights,
creating a magical atmosphere.
Temperatures also drop dramatically, so be sure to wear enough layers.
We travel onwards to Beijing, the nation's capital.
Beijing has a history that goes back more than 3,000 years.
It's the polical center of China, but also brims with culture and creativity.
A good place to start exploring the city is Tiananmen Square,
where Mao Zedong proclaimed the People's Republic of China, in 1949,
an event that changed the course of the country drastically.
Since then, Tiananmen has been used for celebrations and parades,
but was also the epicenter of a suppressed student protest in 1989.
These days, the square is a hotspot for Chinese tourists,
and gets especially busy on national holidays.
Across from Tiananmen lies the Forbidden City, one of the
most interesting historical sites in Beijing.
Off limits for 500 years, hence its name, this is the largest and
best preserved cluster of ancient buildings in China.
Two dynasties of Emperors lived here, who only left the
walled city when they really had to.
Other landmarks in Beijing include the Summer Palace,
and the Temple of Heaven Park,
a beautiful complex of religious buildings in the South of the city.
Watching some of the daily life in the parks,
and some of the remaining 'hutongs',
narrow alleyways in traditional neighborhoods, is one of
the best things you can do in Beijing.
You might come across people playing 'jianzi', best described
as a mix of badminton and football,
or people playing 'mahjong', the classic Chinese tile game.
Don't leave the city without tasting, or at least smelling, Peking Duck,
a dish first served to emperors.
and watching a show of Beijing opera.
Beijing also had a modern face, which you will meet
as you travel through the city.
Head to Wangfujing, to get a sense of the commercial face of Beijing,
or take a look at the impressive stadiums, inside
the 2008 OIympics park.
A must do when in Beijing, is visit the Great Wall,
a series of fortifications that were built along the borders of
ancient Chinese states, and later imperial China.
These stretches were linked when China was unified in the Qing Dynasty, more than 2,000 years ago,
and became known as the Great Wall of China.
Now, the people you see climbing the Wall here can actually not watch this video.
Their internet access is restricted by the Chinese government,
something that is often referred to as the 'Great Firewall of China'.
Many foreign websites and apps are blocked, including Facebook, Instagram, Google, and also Youtube.
Aside from the impact on Chinese society, this can also be very inconvenient for travelers,
something I experienced first hand.
Gladly, there is a service called VPN, meaning Virtual Private Network, that lets you access these sites safely.
Which brings me to the sponsor for this video, Surfshark.
With a Surfshark VPN, you can connect to all your favorite sites, no matter where you are in the world.
Simply open the app, select one of the many servers, and start watching or reading your favorite content.
I always turn on VPN when using public Wifi, also outside China, to make sure my passwords and personal details are secure.
All information sent over Surfshark is encrypted, protecting you from the many digital hazards we face today.
With a VPN you are virtually placing your device in a different country,
which can also come in handy if you want to watch Netflix or other shows that are region specific.
If all this sounds interesting, then Surfshark has a great offer for you, with 3 months extra for free and 83% off.
Simply scan the QR code or click the link in the description, and use my promocode HOFFER.
And, good to know, it has a 30 day money back guarantee.
Now, let's continue our journey through urban China.
By some accounts the largest municipality in China, Chongqing is
a mindboggling place, and our next destination.
Located on the mighty Yangtze river, it has become an
important commercial and transportation hub,
attracting people from around the region and beyond to work and live.
A traveler's first impression of Chongqing can be overwhelming,
as the city is built on steep mountains and hills,
making it somewhat challenging to navigate.
Gladly, a cable car spanning the Yangtze, and a light-railway line,
meandering through the tall skyscrapers, make it easier to get around.
Nevertheless, visitors should be prepared to climb a lot of stairs.
Chongqing lacks the attractions that other cities have, but it's a fascinating place
to witness some of the urbanization process that takes place across the country.
While China used to be a country of farmers, it is quickly
becoming a nation of city dwellers,
and in Chongqing you'll stumble on a constrasting image
at almost every corner.
Old neighborhoods need to make way for shopping malls,
offices, and residential apartment towers,
destroying one way of life, trying to create another.
We continue our journey to Lhasa, the spiritual heartland of Tibet,
located on the 'Rooftop of the World'.
While there are other ways to reach Lhasa, I found the most
interesting one by train,
traveling on the highest railway line in the world, over 5,000 meters at some stretches.
Traversing the rugged, barren Tibetan landscapes proved a beautiful introduction
to arriving in Lhasa, which felt like stepping into a different world.
The first views of the magnificent Potala Palace are unforgettable.
This is the historical seat of the Tibetan government,
and former Winter residence of the Dalai Lama,
the spiritual leader of the Tibetan people, who is currently
living in exile in India.
Tibet has had a tumultuous history, dating back to the 7th century,
and has known periods of independence and occupation,
by Chinese and Mongolian dynasties.
More recently, in 1950, it was invaded by Communist China,
which has ruled the region ever since.
Much has been written about the Tibetan issue, and it's a good idea
to read up before you travel here.
And note that foreign travelers can only visit Tibet as part of a group tour.
A good way to start exploring Lhasa is by joining pilgrims
making a traditional 'kora',
as they walk around the Potala Palace turning prayer wheels
and mumbling mantras.
Kora is a combination of pilgrimage and meditative practices in Tibetan Buddhism.
It's also possible to climb the Potala Palace, but make sure to take your time,
as Lhasa is located at an altitude of over 3,600 meters.
Another spot not to miss is the Sera Monastery, one of the largest in Tibet,
and an important center of education.
Come here for the daily debating session, when monks discuss
philosophical and religious topics inside of their courtyards.
My favorite area in Lhasa is called Barkhor, essentially the
spiritual center of the city.
Countless pilgrims walk around the Jokhang temple,
where they perform prostration,
a ritual meant to purify negative thoughts and bad karma.
Some prostrate all the way from their villages to Lhasa, a journey that can
take several months, but most take part in shorter versions.
After Lhasa, we travel to Central China, to visit Xian,
one of the four ancient Chinese capitals,
located in a region that was at the heart of early Chinese civilization.
Known as Chang'an in the older days, it was at the center of several dynasties,
and flourished as the beginning and end of the historic Silk Road.
Before its demise in the 10th century, this was a place where Chinese culture
and creativity thrived, and many religions coexisted.
While Xian today is mostly a modern city, reminders of its history
are scattered in and around town.
The City Walls, although constructed in the 14th century,
are a good example of how imperial cities were built.
It's almost hard to imagine that the walls of ancient Chang'an
originally enclosed an area seven times larger than this.
One of my favorite spots in Xian is the Muslim neighborhood,
home to the city's Hui community for centuries.
Although the area has undergone many changes, and parts are now
mostly geared towards tourism,
it's still a good place to wander around, meet the people,
and try some of the delicious food.
Xian's most famous place, however, lies outside the city.
The magnificent Terracotta Army is located around 40 kilometers of downtown Xian,
and is one of China's most impressive historic sites.
The Army, consisting of thousands of life size warriors, chariots, and others,
depicts the armies of Qin Shi Huang, the first Emperor of a unified China.
It was built underground, around the tomb of the Emperor,
more than two millennia ago,
and was only discovered in 1974 by local farmers.
We continue our travels to Ordos, a somewhat surreal city in the North of China.
The reason for coming here was to see one of the country's best known 'ghost towns'.
In the Chinese context, these are cities or neighborhoods that are
newly constructed, but where very few people actually live.
The reason these ghost towns exist is simply put for the sake of economic growth.
Many Chinese analysts would say they are investments
into future urbanization,
while global experts argue they are an example of a growing
property bubble and housing crisis in the country.
Walking the largely deserted streets, past lavish, but empty apertment buildings,
and through quiet shopping malls, did feel somewhat eerie.
And as I traveled to other parts of China, such as here in Shenfu,
I couldn't help but wonder what these places would look like in a few decades.
Our next destination lies in far Western China, in the now
controversial Xinjiang province.
Kashgar is, or was, a city like no other.
Surrounded by mountains and deserts, it is closer to Baghdad than Beijing,
and its original inhabitants, the Uyghurs, are closely linked
to the people of Central Asia.
It was an important stop on the ancient Silk Road, and has been at the
crossroads of cultures and religions for over two millennia.
Please note that I visited Kashgar in 2010, and many things have changed since then.
Before being demolished and rebuilt, Kashgar's old town was
where most travelers went,
to get a sense of the traditions and customs of the Uyghur people.
This was where craftsmen had been working for generations, creating
beautiful silverware, clothes, handicrafts, and other things.
The narrow alleyways in these remaining pockets of old town
were filled with activities and charm,
and I could spend hours, if not days, here just soaking up the atmosphere.
And every Sunday, traders from around Kashgar gathered at a massive
livestock market, unrivaled in the region.
Thousands of goats, cows, horses, donkeys, and other animals
invaded the town at sunrise,
accompanied by farmers, nomads and shepherds.
It was a fascinating sight, that could easily be the set of a movie.
These traditional scenes, however, were disappearing quickly,
after the Chinese government made Kashgar, and the entire province of
Xinjiang, a so called 'top priority'.
In recent years, things escalated further, with around a million,
mostly Uyghur people, being detained,
in what the Chinese government calls 're-education camps'.
This process has been condemned globally,
and the treatment of the Uyghurs, in and out of these camps,
has been labeled a crime against humanity,
by the UN and other international organizations.
We can only hope that the situation in this region will somehow improve in the future.
After Kashgar, we travel back to Eastern China, to visit Qingdao,
one of China's most beautiful coastal cities.
Set on the shores of the Yellow Sea, with rolling green hills as
backdrop, it surely is a scenic place.
Many Chinese tourists come here to visit the beaches,
and eat some of the best seafood in the country.
But it was the German architecture that caught my eye when I first arrived here.
German naval officers invaded Qingdao in the late 19th century,
and left their mark on the city, building railway lines, churches,
villas, schools, and even a brewery.
Tsingtao is now one of China's largest beer producers.
Perhaps the most striking building is Saint Michael's Catholic church.
The church has a beautiful interior but equally interesting is
what often takes place on the outside.
Soon to be married brides and grooms, wearing Western style
dresses, take orders from busy camera crews.
The wedding industry is booming in China, with a rising middle class able to
afford more extravagant festivities, including pre wedding photo shoots.
Like many cities in China, Qingdao is also changing rapidly,
and the constrasts become bigger as you move into the suburbs.
Here you can see everything from disappearing neighborhoods
and second hand markets, to wholesale companies and industrial centers.
Qingdao's modern city center feels entirely different.
It's only a short taxi or subway ride away from the old town,
but I suggest using the waterfront promenade where you can
walk through some beautiful areas of the city.
We follow the coastline all the way South, to visit Hong Kong,
seen by many as the perfect fusion between East and West,
and one of my favorite cities in the world.
It's a modern metropolis, but also a cultural powerhouse.
It's easy to fall in love with Hong Kong at first sight,
with its amazing skyline and backdrop of green mountains,
but for many this is only where the story begins.
The city was part of Britain for almost a century,
the result of negotiations with the Chinese empire,
after the infamous Opium Wars.
Over the years, with ups and downs, the people of Hong Kong managed
to build a flourishing society with democratic freedoms and their own identity.
Some of these freedoms, however, have come under pressure,
after the city was handed back to China in 1997.
Recently, the city has seen massive protest, with people
voicing their concern over China's growing influence.
One of the best ways to start exploring Hong Kong, is to
visit the spectacular Victoria Peak,
from where you can admire the jaw-dropping urban landscape of the city.
You can reach the Peak by taxi or on a steep hike,
but most travelers use the historic Victoria Peak Tram,
a gravity defying attraction that should not be missed.
Another way to appreciate the city's skyline is to sail the
classic Star Ferry, across Victoria Harbour.
For just a few Hong Kong dollars, this is probably
the best valued trip in the city.
Hong Kong is a breeze to get around, and boasts a very efficient
public transport system, including an extensive metro network,
double deck trams, and even helicopters for those who can afford it.
For some travelers, Hong Kong is a shopper's paradise.
And sometimes it feels like the city is one giant shopping mall,
as many buildings are connected by airconditioned walkways.
Others come here for the Cantonese food, which is some of the best in Asia.
From luxurious restaurants to street food markets and local eateries,
there is something for everyone.
For a different side of Hong Kong, head to some of the tranquil islands,
or visit the Big Buddha statue, located in a major Buddhist
center in the mountains.
But it's the streets of Kowloon district and beyond,
that really make me love Hong Kong.
This is the cultural heartland of the city, where traditional
neighborhoods mix with bustling street markets.
It feels overwhelming in some parts, yet surprisingly peaceful in others.
Visit one of the many temples, browse some of the markets,
sample local cuisine,
or simply wander around and be surprised by this magnificent city.
A stone's throw away from Hong Kong lies Macau, a former
Portuguese enclave that is known as the 'Las Vegas of the East'.
Its skyline is dominated by some of the world's largest casinos,
and parts of the city have turned into massive entertainment centers.
The reason for its popularity is simple, it's the only place
in China where gambling is legal.
But Macau also has a different face, with a Portuguese influence
that is still visible today, in its architecture, food, and culture.
Even though you'll share the streets with a lot of tourists,
it's a fun and interesting place to spend a day or two.
Bordering Hong Kong on the North, Shenzhen is one of China's
most remarkable cities, and our next destination.
A small fishing village merely 40 years ago, Shenzhen has grown
into one of the country's largest and wealthiest cities.
It attracts businesspeople, migrant workers, and investors
from around the country and the world,
all chasing the 'Chinese economic dream'.
Shenzhen became a so called 'Special Economic Zone',
an idea brought forward by Deng Xiaoping,
who led a series of market economy reforms,
that propelled the growth of China.
Since then, Shenzhen has become China's largest electronics manufacturing
hub, and is now a leading high-tech center.
For travelers, Shenzhen may not offer a lot of sights.
But there are plenty of parks, shopping centers, and a surprising
theme park that can keep you busy.
In general, I found Shenzhen a young and dynamic place where you can get a sense
of China's urbanization and economic expansion of the past decades.
While you can get around China in numerous ways, the high-speed
railway network is by far the most convenient,
especially when you travel between larger cities.
Because of their size, the train stations can sometimes feel intimidating
to navigate, but once you understand the system, it's all quite straightforward.
We travel back to Central China, to visit Wuhan,
a city that will forever be linked to the global pandemic,
that changed our world so abruptly.
I visited Wuhan twice before this all started, and met a sprawling city,
with massive bridges spanning the Yangtze river, busy shopping streets,
but also some charismatic old neighborhoods.
Wuhan is actually a combination of three formerly independent cities,
that have grown into one huge metropolis.
Its history is often compared to Shanghai, with its concession era buildings
and commercial energy, but the city also has its own distinct character.
One of the most iconic buildings here is the Yellow Crane Tower,
from where you can see much of the city's skyline,
and also the historic Wuhan Yangte River bridge.
This double-deck road and rail bridge was the first modern bridge to
span the Yangtze river, and was completed in 1957.
We finish this journey through urban China in Guangzhou,
a fascinating city located in the Pearl River Delta.
It's a center of Cantonese culture and has grown into a major
trading and business hub over the years.
While skyscrapers dominate the skyline, Guangzhou also has a
variety of neighborhoods with a more relaxed atmosphere.
Downtown Guangzhou is filled with modern office towers, shopping malls,
and a massive football stadium, and is really the commercial heart of the city.
But as you make your way through town, you'll also meet
the other faces of Guangzhou.
The pedestrian only Shamian island, for instance, is filled with
historic mansions and villas.
Also impressive in the Sacred Heart cathedral,
while the nearby riverside promenade is perfect for an evening stroll.
And in the suburbs, I found this traditional South Chinese garden, called Baomo,
filled with temples and classic bridges.
But in the evenings, when the neon lights go on, Guangzhou is
unmistakably a Chinese megacity again.
And that concludes my journey through urban China.
I realize I have only scratched the surface, and you could spend months,
if not years, exploring these places.
Yet I still hope this video gave you some travel ideas,
or at least provided a glimpse into these captivating but complicated cities.
Thanks for watching this video, and I hope to see you again next time.
Travel safely.